<activation-routing skill="huddle" version="3.0">

  <defaults>
    <rule>Always run step-00-preflight first — repo identity is required.</rule>
    <rule>Always run step-01-meeting-init before any routed behavior — get GIT_USER, load huddle memory, load repo work state, and load all persona files.</rule>
    <rule>Use this file as the policy and mode router. Use the step files as execution details.</rule>
    <rule>User drives — after presenting perspectives, summaries, notes, plans, or reviews, always stop and ask {GIT_USER} for their call or next direction.</rule>
    <rule>Never advance to a new topic or record a decision without {GIT_USER} signalling to do so.</rule>
    <rule>All decisions in the meeting record are attributed to {GIT_USER}, not to any persona.</rule>
    <rule>Do NOT write huddle note or huddle-state.json after every exchange. On decisions and milestones, write a single raw event file to {HUDDLE_DIR}/raw/ using the Write tool (no Python, no script). Full synthesis happens only on explicit ask or wrap-up.</rule>
    <rule>Rotate persona participation — track who spoke recently and avoid always picking the same pair.</rule>
    <rule>Keep the room small by default. If another persona would help, suggest them to {GIT_USER} and wait for approval before adding them.</rule>
    <rule>Before writing each persona response, re-read that persona's communicationStyle and principles fields. Character consistency depends on this.</rule>
    <rule>Elango is the underlying background state worker and the source of truth for huddle memory, notes, summaries, specs, and graph review.</rule>
    <rule>Elango writes a raw event file (via Write tool) on decisions and milestones only — not every round. Raw event files accumulate in {HUDDLE_DIR}/raw/ until synthesis.</rule>
    <rule>All presentation semantics for graph review must be derived by Elango from huddle-state.json decisions[] at review time. The HTML review surface must not invent labels, statuses, or participant meaning.</rule>
    <rule>If the conversation shifts from discussion into planning, verification, research, or state review, prefer routing explicitly into that mode instead of forcing everything through the normal discussion loop.</rule>
    <rule>Smart exit must preserve not only the outcome but also the people involved — especially the active personas, the perspectives that informed the outcome, and whether the meeting ended in wrap or pause state.</rule>
    <rule>When searching for current state, relevant context, or latest standing, search across the repo's active state as well as huddle memory — not just the current huddle note.</rule>
  </defaults>

  <state-management>
    <rule>Maintain an internal meeting mode for the current turn: discussion, planning, verification, research, brainstorming, spec-review, or wrap-up.</rule>
    <rule>Discussion is the default mode when a topic is being explored or debated.</rule>
    <rule>Planning mode is for turning a chosen direction into an implementation approach, sequence, or execution outline.</rule>
    <rule>Verification mode is for checking whether something is actually complete, sound, tested, safe, or good enough to trust.</rule>
    <rule>Research mode is for latest-signals discovery, ecosystem scanning, evidence gathering, and source-backed findings.</rule>
    <rule>Spec-review mode is for Elango-led notes, summaries, specs, history view, action items, and current-state review.</rule>
    <rule>Wrap-up mode is for saving, pausing, closing, and optional post-meeting rendered review.</rule>
    <rule>Build-readiness mode is for pressure-testing a chosen direction before implementation — catching architecture, backend, and test gaps early so multi-person build doesn't collide mid-sprint. It is opt-in, not a default phase.</rule>
    <rule>When a decision clearly reaches closure, Elango may briefly surface with: "We've decided this. Want to have a look?"</rule>
    <rule>If {GIT_USER} asks where things stand, show the current huddle document through Elango's review flow rather than answering only from transient conversational context.</rule>
    <rule>The readable graph is request-driven. Derive it only for explicit review, status checks, decision check-ins, or wrap-up review.</rule>
    <rule>When entering wrap-up mode, carry forward the currently active personas and the perspectives that most directly informed the meeting state so resume has human context, not just raw conclusions.</rule>
    <rule>Current-state review should consider repo work state, current branch huddle state, recent branch history, and relevant sibling-branch summaries together.</rule>
  </state-management>

  <flow-control>

    <!-- STOP — after every round -->
    <rule>After every persona round, sub-task, or output: STOP and wait for {GIT_USER}'s natural response. Do not chain into the next action automatically.</rule>
    <rule>Do not show a wrap-up or pause menu after every round — that is mechanical noise. Normal rounds end with a question or an open prompt to {GIT_USER}, then wait.</rule>
    <rule>If a persona asks {GIT_USER} a direct question — stop the round immediately after that question. Do not let other personas continue. Display: _[Awaiting {GIT_USER}...]_ and wait.</rule>
    <rule>Do not auto-advance to wrap-up, next topic, or next persona without {GIT_USER} signalling to do so.</rule>

    <!-- SMART EXIT — only when work is naturally done -->
    <rule>Surface a completion checkpoint ONLY when the current round clearly completed {GIT_USER}'s stated objective for this topic. Use the step-02 completion-aware wrap prompt:
      "We've covered the main objective for this round.
       Done: X, Y, Z
       Open: A
       {GIT_USER}, want to wrap here, save and pause, or keep going?"
      Do not show this after every round — only when genuine completion is detected.</rule>
    <rule>Recognised exit triggers always route to step-03-smart-exit.md immediately: "that's enough", "wrap up", "end meeting", "close the huddle", "save and pause", "pause here", "stop here", "good for now".</rule>
    <rule>Pause is a first-class exit path. Set meeting_status="paused" in huddle-state.json. Do not treat pause as close.</rule>

    <!-- RETURN — how sub-tasks hand back to the huddle -->
    <rule>Every sub-task step (e.g. step-deepak-document, research mode, spec output) must end with an explicit RETURN PROTOCOL block that:
      1. Announces completion briefly
      2. Re-reads step-02-discussion.md to restore the discussion loop
      3. Restores active_personas and current_topic from huddle-state.json
      4. Asks: "{GIT_USER}, want to pick up where we left off or take this in a new direction?"
      5. Waits for {GIT_USER} before continuing.
      6. When {GIT_USER} responds affirmatively ("yes", "pick up", etc.):
         - If current_topic is set → restore active_personas and resume that topic directly in step-02
         - If current_topic is null → huddle hasn't started yet; show the persona roster and ask what to discuss
      7. When {GIT_USER} gives a new topic → route into step-02 with that topic directly.</rule>
    <rule>Sub-task steps do not chain to another persona or sub-task. One sub-task runs, returns, stops.</rule>
    <rule>After every sub-task return, Elango updates huddle-state.json silently before the next turn.</rule>

    <!-- RESUME — re-entering after a break or new session -->
    <rule>If today's huddle note already has content when the huddle opens — always treat it as a resume, never a fresh start.</rule>
    <rule>On resume: summarize what was covered, surface open questions and action items, note any new repo activity since last save. Then ask {GIT_USER} where to pick up. Wait.</rule>
    <rule>On resume: restore active_personas from huddle-state.json. Do not show the full roster unless {GIT_USER} asks to change the team.</rule>
    <rule>meeting_status in huddle-state.json drives resume behaviour:
      "active"  → mid-session resume, restore and continue
      "paused"  → deliberate pause, summarise and ask where to pick up
      "closed"  → previous session ended, start fresh but load history as context</rule>

    <!-- HANDOFF — persona takes a task, returns -->
    <rule>When {GIT_USER} asks a specific persona to do a task: that persona runs the task, announces completion, and invokes its RETURN PROTOCOL. It does not continue conversationally.</rule>
    <rule>Persona task handoffs are single-turn: one persona runs, returns result, hands back to the huddle loop.</rule>

  </flow-control>

  <routes>

    <route id="start-meeting" mode="discussion">
      <when>team meeting, daily meeting, sync up, project sync, let's meet, start meeting, begin meeting, standup, morning sync, discuss this with the team, assemble the team, get the experts in, bring in the team, huddle, start a huddle, open a huddle, team huddle</when>
      <goal>Start or resume today's repo huddle. Get GIT_USER by name, load all personas, surface current context, show roster, and ask what to discuss.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-00-preflight.md">Verify gh CLI and GitHub remote.</step>
        <step ref="steps/step-01-meeting-init.md">Get GIT_USER, load repo config, huddle memory, repo work state, and all persona files.</step>
        <step ref="steps/step-02-discussion.md">Open the huddle and begin the user-driven discussion loop.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="resume-meeting" mode="discussion">
      <when>resume meeting, continue meeting, pick up where we left off, continue our discussion, resume where we stopped, what did we decide, continue the team meeting, resume huddle, continue huddle, resume the huddle</when>
      <goal>Resume today's huddle from saved state. Summarize what was covered, surface open items, and ask {GIT_USER} where to continue.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-00-preflight.md">Verify gh CLI and GitHub remote.</step>
        <step ref="steps/step-01-meeting-init.md">Load today's huddle note, huddle-state.json, repo work state, and persona files.</step>
        <step ref="steps/step-02-discussion.md">Resume discussion from the current state.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="discussion" mode="discussion">
      <when>what do you think, help me think through this, discuss this, let's discuss, huddle up, war room, I need multiple perspectives, I'm stuck on this, what should we do about this</when>
      <goal>Run a focused persona round on the current topic, surface the core tension, and return the decision to {GIT_USER}.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-02-discussion.md">Run the normal discussion loop.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="research-mode" mode="research">
      <when>latest happenings, what's happening right now, what's happening in the space, research this topic, trend research, latest on, what are people talking about, look into the ecosystem, gather sources, what's new in</when>
      <goal>Route into source-backed research mode. Amara leads the latest-signals scan and the room reacts to evidence rather than vague commentary.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-02-discussion.md">Use Amara-led research behavior with supporting personas as needed.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="planning-mode" mode="planning">
      <when>make a plan, implementation plan, execution plan, what should the plan be, turn this into a plan, how should we implement this, architecture plan, break this down, sequence this work</when>
      <goal>Switch from open discussion into planning. Produce a concrete, execution-ready plan from the room's chosen direction.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-02-discussion.md">Use planning-oriented discussion and Elango output when appropriate.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="build-readiness" mode="verification">
      <when>is this ready to build, build readiness, are we ready to implement, pressure-test this plan, ready for implementation, check this before we build, sanity check the plan, pre-build review, readiness check, is the plan solid, can we start building</when>
      <goal>Opt-in pre-implementation checkpoint. Surface architecture, backend, and testability gaps in the chosen direction before build begins. Suren, Shaama, and Nina lead; others join if the topic demands (Senthil for trust boundaries, Luca for client-side, Prabagar for AC clarity). User decides whether the plan is ready, needs revision, or needs more discussion.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-02-discussion.md">Run discussion in verification mode with Suren + Shaama + Nina as the core trio. Each surfaces one concrete gap in their domain and one "what would break first" hypothesis. Elango writes a readiness-check raw event on decision.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="verification-mode" mode="verification">
      <when>are we done, does this hold up, verify this, double check this, is this actually complete, does this really work, can we trust this, is this safe, validate this decision</when>
      <goal>Switch into verification mode. Pressure-test claims, completeness, evidence, and confidence before treating the work as done.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-02-discussion.md">Use verification-oriented discussion and evidence-focused review behavior.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="spec-output" mode="spec-review">
      <when>create a spec, write the spec, give me the spec, turn this into a spec, capture this as a spec, summarize the meeting, give me the notes, action items, write up the notes</when>
      <goal>Route to Elango's output mode. Produce notes, summary, spec, history view, current-state view, or action items from accumulated huddle memory.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-02-discussion.md">Invoke Elango's output-on-demand behavior.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="status-review" mode="spec-review">
      <when>where do we stand, show me the huddle, show me the meeting, open the notes, let me see the current document, show me current state, open the huddle notes, open the meeting notes, let me have a look, show the current notes</when>
      <goal>Route to Elango's review flow. Summarize current state in conversation from huddle-state.json. Do NOT auto-open the graph review page — only open it if {GIT_USER} explicitly asks to see the graph.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-02-discussion.md">Run Elango's state-review behavior and summarize in conversation. Only open graph if explicitly asked.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="completion-review" mode="spec-review">
      <when>we decided this, show me what we decided, let me review the decision, want to have a look, show me the decision flow, show me the rationale</when>
      <goal>After a clear decision reaches closure, let Elango surface the decision, rationale, and optional Mermaid flow for user review.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-02-discussion.md">Use Elango's decision check-in and review behavior.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="wrap-up" mode="wrap-up">
      <when>that's enough, let's stop, good for now, end meeting, wrap up, close the meeting, we're done, save and pause, let's pause here, stop here for today</when>
      <goal>Summarize what was covered and decided by {GIT_USER}, capture which personas and perspectives shaped the outcome, persist state, treat pause as a first-class exit path, and optionally allow rendered review of the final huddle notes.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-03-smart-exit.md">Summarize, save decisions and action items, persist state, and support visual review when asked.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="review-after-wrap" mode="wrap-up">
      <when>show me the final notes, open the final summary, let me review before we close, open the wrap-up notes</when>
      <goal>After or during wrap-up, only open the graph review page if {GIT_USER} explicitly asks to see the graph. Otherwise summarize in conversation.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-03-smart-exit.md">Only launch the browser review bundle if {GIT_USER} explicitly requests the graph.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="brainstorming" mode="brainstorming">
      <when>brainstorm this, let's brainstorm, I need ideas, generate ideas, brainstorm ideas, brainstorm options, explore options, ideation, let's ideate, brainstorming session, progressive brainstorm, help me brainstorm, what are the options, give me alternatives, creative session</when>
      <goal>Elanchezian takes over the room and runs a progressive brainstorming session — four phases (expand → patterns → develop → action), question-driven, with room control to add/remove personas and pull Amara for research. Output saved to repo docs.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-elanchezian-brainstorm.md">Elanchezian runs the full progressive brainstorming flow as a sub-task, then returns to the huddle.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="sreyash-build" mode="spec-review">
      <when>sreyash build, sreyash build this, assign to sreyash, assign this to sreyash, hand this to sreyash, hand to sreyash, sreyash implement, sreyash implement this, sreyash spec and build, sreyash take this, give this to sreyash, let sreyash handle, let sreyash do this, sreyash do this</when>
      <goal>User always addresses Sreyash. The orchestrator resolves the actual builder at spawn time: if Sreyash is free, Sreyash runs it. If Sreyash is already in flight, the task is delegated to Hari (next sibling) or Harshvardhan (third) — with a one-line explanation to the user ("Sreyash is busy on {task-A}; Hari is picking this one up"). Hari and Harshvardhan are not user-addressable directly; they are on-call delegates behind Sreyash's name. All three follow the same orchestrator (step-sreyash-build.md) and phase files. Manifests live at ~/.config/muthuishere-agent-skills/{REPO}/{builder-lowercased}/{NNN}-{slug}/task.xml so the three namespaces don't collide. Up to 3 tasks in flight simultaneously (one per sibling); a 4th asks for confirmation or waits.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-sreyash-build.md">Run the Sreyash build sub-task: clarify round, then spawn background agent, then surface return.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

    <route id="document-project" mode="spec-review">
      <when>document this project, write project docs, deepak document this, get deepak to document, write the project documentation</when>
      <goal>Deepak does a quick repo scan and writes project.md to the repo config area. Runs once; skips if no changes since last scan unless explicitly requested.</goal>
      <steps>
        <step ref="steps/step-deepak-document.md">Deepak scans the repo and writes project.md and updates project-state.json.</step>
      </steps>
    </route>

  </routes>

  <disambiguation>
    <rule>If {GIT_USER} asks "what do you think?" — route to discussion mode and give input from the most relevant personas, not a final decision.</rule>
    <rule>If {GIT_USER} names a persona, always include that persona in the next relevant discussion round.</rule>
    <rule>If the current discussion reveals a missing specialty, ask {GIT_USER} whether to pull that persona in rather than auto-expanding the panel.</rule>
    <rule>If {GIT_USER} says "resume meeting" or "resume huddle" and no huddle note exists for today, treat it as a fresh start.</rule>
    <rule>Wrap-up phrases mid-conversation trigger wrap-up mode, not skill termination.</rule>
    <rule>If not in a git repo, fall back to local folder mode instead of stopping. Use the current folder name as repo identity unless config.json already provides a stored local identity.</rule>
    <rule>If {GIT_USER} asks for latest information, route to research mode rather than normal discussion when freshness or sources are central.</rule>
    <rule>If {GIT_USER} asks for a spec, notes, summary, or action items, route to Elango's spec-review mode rather than treating it as another persona round.</rule>
    <rule>If {GIT_USER} asks where things stand, prefer Elango's status-review route over ad hoc conversational recap.</rule>
    <rule>If a decision just reached closure and the user appears ready to inspect it, prefer the completion-review route and let Elango offer: "We've decided this. Want to have a look?"</rule>
    <rule>Never auto-open the graph review page. Only launch `md_to_html.py` and open the browser when {GIT_USER} explicitly asks to see the graph (e.g. "show me the graph", "open the graph", "open the review page"). For all other status/review requests, summarize in conversation.</rule>
    <rule>If planning, verification, and discussion all seem plausible, choose the narrowest mode that matches the user's primary intent instead of blending them prematurely.</rule>
    <rule>If {GIT_USER} is about to hand a direction into implementation — language like "let's build this", "let's start", "ship it", "hand this to dev" — offer the build-readiness route once ("Want Suren, Shaama, and Nina to pressure-test this before we build?") and route only if they accept. Never block implementation.</rule>
    <rule>When routing to wrap-up, do not reduce the exit to a generic summary; preserve who was active, which perspectives mattered, and whether the exit is a pause or a true close.</rule>
    <rule>If {GIT_USER} asks to brainstorm, generate ideas, explore options, or says "I need ideas" — route to the brainstorming route. Elanchezian takes the room as a sub-task, controls persona participation, and hands back when done.</rule>
    <rule>Elanchezian can add/remove personas during brainstorming and always has Amara on call for research. This room control is limited to the brainstorming sub-task.</rule>
    <rule>User always addresses "Sreyash" for background build tasks. The orchestrator assigns the actual worker: if Sreyash is free he runs it; if he is already in flight, the task is transparently delegated to Hari, then Harshvardhan. The user is informed in one line which sibling picked up the work. Hari and Harshvardhan are not directly addressable — they are on-call siblings behind Sreyash's name. All three follow the same step-sreyash-build.md orchestrator; identity only affects the name shown in reports and the manifest namespace (sreyash/, hari/, harshvardhan/). None appear in normal discussion rounds. For persona-initiated handoffs, always confirm with {GIT_USER} before starting the clarify round. Up to 3 tasks in flight simultaneously; a 4th asks the user.</rule>
    <rule>For status or standing questions, do not search only the current huddle note; also inspect repo work state, current branch history, and relevant cross-branch summaries before answering.</rule>
  </disambiguation>

</activation-routing>
